<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>general on trang1618</title>
    <link>/tags/general/</link>
    <description>Recent content in general on trang1618</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 17:27:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A New, Shiny Website!</title>
      <link>/archives/2012-04-01-a-new-shiny-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 17:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2012-04-01-a-new-shiny-website/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve finally got this new website built using
[Jekyll](https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll) and migrated my old content
over. I&#39;ve been looking to move to a new system for a while - one that
would fit with my workflow and help me keep a blog as an [open lab
notebook](http://www.carlboettiger.info/archives/211).
[Squarespace](http://www.squarespace.com) was a great place to start a
blog, but a Jekyll site hosted on [Github](www.github.com) is (A)
faster, (B) free, (C) more customizable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links and Resources</title>
      <link>/archives/2012-04-01-links-and-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 16:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2012-04-01-links-and-resources/</guid>
      <description>*(Material migrated over from my old website)*

**Blogs and News Sources**

-   [Grist](http://www.grist.org/), especially [David
    Roberts](http://www.grist.org/people/David+Roberts)&#39; sharp political
    commentary
-   [Resilience Science](http://rs.resalliance.org/), by Garry Peterson.
    See also the [Resilience
    Wiki](http://wiki.resalliance.org/index.php/Main_Page) and the
    [Resilience Alliance](http://www.resalliance.org/1.php)
-   [Conservation Bytes](http://conservationbytes.com/), a blog on</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extinction debt, dark diversity, and how things are much worse than they look</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-11-28-extinction-debt-dark-diversity-and-how-things-are-much-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-11-28-extinction-debt-dark-diversity-and-how-things-are-much-worse/</guid>
      <description>I discovered this unpublished post today, originally written in the Spring:
A while ago I wrote a wikipedia article on extinction debt. &amp;nbsp;Frankly, researching this topic scared the hell out of me. Extinction debt began as a fairly obscure theoretical concept that emerged out of mathematical modeling exercises in ecology that showed that it could take tens or even hundreds of years for species to go extinct (Timan et al. 1994).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Novel Ecosystems Do the Job of &#34;Natural&#34; Ones?</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-09-01-can-novel-ecosystems-do-the-job-of-natural-ones/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-09-01-can-novel-ecosystems-do-the-job-of-natural-ones/</guid>
      <description>This week in Science, Shahid Naeem reviews two books&amp;nbsp;(paywall) about modern, &#34;novel&#34; ecosystems, which humans have created by mixing together species that never evolved together. &amp;nbsp;He wonders, are such systems Frankensteins?  Modern ecosystems that are haphazardly&amp;nbsp;assembled from the remains of human&amp;nbsp;development are unpredictable and fragile. With one billion people hungry, two&amp;nbsp;billion poor and three billion in desperate need of water, the hopes of humanity rest on conserving, restoring and&amp;nbsp;sustainably managing the services that&amp;nbsp;nature provides.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change and Credit Risk in the Chemicals Sector</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-02-22-climate-change-and-credit-risk-in-the-chemicals-sector/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-02-22-climate-change-and-credit-risk-in-the-chemicals-sector/</guid>
      <description>WRI continues the march of environmentally-driven credit analyses&amp;nbsp;with a new report on the chemical sector and how climate regulation could effect industry&#39;s ability to borrow. &amp;nbsp;WRI looks at both congressionally- and EPA-driven scenarios for greenhouse gas regulation and maps how different chemical sub-sectors will be affected in each.

Differences between cap-and-trade legislation and EPA-implemented regulation are interesting and not entirely intuitive. &amp;nbsp;For instance, based on previous attempts at cap-and-trade, legislation will probably provide free emissions permits to emissions-intense sectors for the first decade or so, leaving&amp;nbsp;medium&amp;nbsp;emitters the most exposed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Delving into the Green Economy Report</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-02-21-delving-into-the-green-economy-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-02-21-delving-into-the-green-economy-report/</guid>
      <description>UNEP published the&amp;nbsp;Green Economy Report&amp;nbsp;(GER) today. &amp;nbsp;I&#39;ve been looking forward to reading this as it comes from the team that produced the impressive Economics of Ecosystems and Biodiversity Study&amp;nbsp;(TEEB).
TEEB aimed to be the &#34;Stern report&#34; for biodiversity, but it was very different piece of work. &amp;nbsp; GER, on the other hand, does something very similar to Stern - it lays out contrasting scenarios for global investment and explores their consequences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Billabongs, Weevils, and Alternative Stable States</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-02-03-of-billabongs-weevils-and-alternative-stable-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-02-03-of-billabongs-weevils-and-alternative-stable-states/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve heard the song &#34;Waltzing Matilda&#34; many times but I only learned today the meaning of the word&amp;nbsp;billabong&amp;nbsp;- a long lake formed by a river jumping its bed. (In America we call them oxbow lakes.)
    The billabongs of Australia&#39;s Kakadu National Park are the site of a revealing ecological phenomenon reported today in Nature by Anthony Ives and colleagues. &amp;nbsp;Kariba weed, an invasive fern, arrived in the lakes in 1983, but has been kept somewhat in check through the deliberate introduction of the silvinia weevil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tipping Points and the Precautionary Principle</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-01-24-tipping-points-and-the-precautionary-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-01-24-tipping-points-and-the-precautionary-principle/</guid>
      <description>Many ecological systems have tipping points - thresholds where small changes in impacts can have very large effects on on ecosystem functioning, often in a bad way. &amp;nbsp;Lakes, for example, might show little impact from nutrient pollution until a threshold level is reached, and then massive algal blooms form that choke off many other species growth.
In the absence of knowledge of exactly how far one can push a system before reaching a tipping point, many invoke the&amp;nbsp;precautionary principle, which states that in the face of uncertainty, one should take the most conservative approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>George Sugihara on Early Warnings</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-01-17-george-sugihara-on-early-warnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-01-17-george-sugihara-on-early-warnings/</guid>
      <description>In SEED Magazine, theoretical biologist George Sugihara writes about early warning signals for collapses in complex systems:
 A key phenomenon known for decades is so-called &amp;ldquo;critical slowing&amp;rdquo; as a threshold approaches. That is, a system&amp;rsquo;s dynamic response to external perturbations becomes more sluggish near tipping points. Mathematically, this property gives rise to increased inertia in the ups and downs of things like temperature or population numbers&amp;mdash;we call this inertia &amp;ldquo;autocorrelation&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;which in turn can result in larger swings, or more volatility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My article on rural abandonment and ecosystem services at GOOD</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-01-17-my-article-on-rural-abandonment-and-ecosystem-services-at-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-01-17-my-article-on-rural-abandonment-and-ecosystem-services-at-go/</guid>
      <description>I have an article up at GOOD magazine about the abandoned rural lands and how to manage them for ecosystem services:
 Brazil has had a declining rural population since 1990. Even as loggers and farmers cut and burn ancient rainforest in the south, emigrants leave northern farmlands fallow. In China, between just 2000 and 2008, the countryside lost 86 million people. The United Nations projects that the world&amp;rsquo;s total rural population will begin to decline in the 2020s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jellyfish and Ocean Tipping Points</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-01-15-jellyfish-and-ocean-tipping-points/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-01-15-jellyfish-and-ocean-tipping-points/</guid>
      <description>Over at Yale Environment 360, Richard Stone has an interesting article about ongoing work examining recent blooms of jellyfish populations. &amp;nbsp;Anecdotal evidence suggests that jellyfish populations have been on the rise, and it is possible that some marine systems are entering alternate stable states that are jellyfish- rather than fish-dominated:
 By removing a curb on jellyfish population growth, overfishing &amp;ldquo;opens up ecological space for jellyfish,&amp;rdquo; says Anthony Richardson, an ecologist at CSIRO Marine and Atmospheric Research in Cleveland, Australia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REDD&#43; and Financial Resilience for Conservation</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-01-07-redd-and-financial-resilience-for-conservation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-01-07-redd-and-financial-resilience-for-conservation/</guid>
      <description>This month&#39;s&amp;nbsp;Conservation Letters has a Policy Perspective&amp;nbsp;on the risks of relying REDD+ funding for conservation projects. &amp;nbsp;REDD+ (Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and Degradation, with the &#34;+&#34; standing for biodiversity and social benefits), is a mechanism for&amp;nbsp;transferring&amp;nbsp;funds to developing countries for forest preservation and restoration. &amp;nbsp;REDD+ financing is eventually supposed to flow primarily from the private sector, and it is one of the few parts of an international climate agreement that has been uncontentious in negotiations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for unexpected opportunities in Borneo</title>
      <link>/archives/2011-01-02-preparing-for-unexpected-opportunities-in-borneo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2011-01-02-preparing-for-unexpected-opportunities-in-borneo/</guid>
      <description>Conservation Letters&amp;nbsp;has an article&amp;nbsp;about a situation in Borneo that illustrates how sudden, unpredictable events in ecology are not always bad. &amp;nbsp;In the past year, the island&#39;s forests have undergone an ecosystem-wide event known as &#34;general flowering,&#34; where trees of many species produce seeds and fruit in massive amounts. &amp;nbsp;These events occur rarely (the last was 12 years ago), and in the years in between few seeds are produced and few new trees take root.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tackling investor risk in forest restoration</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-12-21-tackling-investor-risk-in-forest-restoration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-12-21-tackling-investor-risk-in-forest-restoration/</guid>
      <description>Ecosystem Marketplace posted an interesting document today on&amp;nbsp;Global Forest Carbon Financial Risk Management Best Practices. &amp;nbsp;Produced as part of a workshop of forest investors and lawyers, it outlines the risks in the forest carbon offset market and practices to manage these risks. &amp;nbsp;Given the growth potential of forest carbon offset markets (not to mention other ecosystem service markets), the risk management tools for offset transactions are underdeveloped. &amp;nbsp;
The authors document 25 different categories of risk that need to be addressed in order to develop the market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing New Invasion Risks from Biofuel Crops</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-12-16-managing-new-invasion-risks-from-biofuel-crops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-12-16-managing-new-invasion-risks-from-biofuel-crops/</guid>
      <description>The search for new biofuels has effectively created an entire new category of agriculture,&amp;nbsp;along with which comes a host of new&amp;nbsp;management risks.&amp;nbsp; The cycles of crop growth and failure may be less well known than those of more familiar food crops, and&amp;nbsp;they may be affected by new pests and disease.
A particularly worrisome area of risk associated with biofuel crops is the possibility that the crops themselves may become noxious pests in countries to which they are imported.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good environmental management lowers cost of borrowing</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-12-06-good-environmental-management-lowers-cost-of-borrowing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-12-06-good-environmental-management-lowers-cost-of-borrowing/</guid>
      <description>Today the RiskMetrics Group ESG Blog highlights new research showing that companies with better environmental performance are viewed as lower risk in bond markets and pay a lower cost of borrowing. &amp;nbsp;The researchers, Rob Bauer and Daniel Hann, won the Moskowitz Prize for research in socially responsible investing. &amp;nbsp;I found this the most interesting finding:
 ...the link between environmental risk and debt costs has strengthened over time. To test this, Bauer and Hann divided their 1995-2006 data sample into two parts, and performed the same tests on data from the 1995-2001 and 2001-2006 periods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fishing for metrics</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-11-20-fishing-for-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-11-20-fishing-for-metrics/</guid>
      <description>In 1998, Dan Pauly et al. of the University of British Columbia published a classic paper&amp;nbsp;called &#34;Fishing Down Marine Food Webs.&#34; They reported that humans were steadily depleting oceans of the top predators in the food web and working our way down the food web as the fish ran out. &amp;nbsp;Pauly measured a value called &#34;Mean Tropic Level,&#34; (MTL), essentially the average place in the food web that our fish come from, finding that it had declined in fisheries globally since the 1970s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apparently, there&#39;s nothing left to learn about ecosystem services</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-11-17-apparently-theres-nothing-left-to-learn-about-ecosystem-serv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-11-17-apparently-theres-nothing-left-to-learn-about-ecosystem-serv/</guid>
      <description>In a new paper in Ecological Economics, Mark Sagoff criticizes ecologists for trying to find general, broadly applicable values for ecosystem services. Real values, Sagoff argues, are &#34;dispersed, contingent, particular, local, transitory, and embedded in institutions and practices.&#34; He cites an example of citrus growers in the San Joaquin valley of California. While pollinators have been held up by many ecologists as providers of a valuable ecosystem services, pollinators are a pest to these farmers:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PricewaterhouseCoopers gets into the ecosystem services game</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-11-14-pricewaterhousecoopers-gets-into-the-ecosystem-services-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-11-14-pricewaterhousecoopers-gets-into-the-ecosystem-services-game/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve noticed a rise lately in the frequency of times I see the name PricewaterhouseCoopers pop up in research about ecosystem services and economics. &amp;nbsp; Most recently they have produced a series of reports&amp;nbsp;with the United Nations Development Program on habitat banking in Latin America and the Carribean. &amp;nbsp;Habitat banking is an ecosystem service market in which habitat &#34;developers&#34; protect or restore ecosystems to generate credits that can be bought by other developers as part of a requirement to mitigate damage caused by construction projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What do we do with forecasts of the future?</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-28-what-do-we-do-with-forecasts-of-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-28-what-do-we-do-with-forecasts-of-the-future/</guid>
      <description>Via Garry Peterson &amp;nbsp;I discovered this post by Simon Donner&amp;nbsp;about forecasts of this year&#39;smassive coral bleaching event in the Caribbean.
Donner and colleagues published a paper in PNAS in 2007&amp;nbsp;in which they calculated that heat waves that cause massive coral bleaching, like a previous event in 2005, had gone from being 1-in-1000-year events to a probability of once every 10-50 years during the 1990s, and by the 2030s will occur every 1-2 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinking about TEEB</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-23-thinking-about-teeb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-23-thinking-about-teeb/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been reading the latest report from The Economics of Ecosystems and Biodiversity (TEEB) study, &amp;nbsp;which was released this week at the meeting for the Convention for Biological Diversity. &amp;nbsp;I&#39;ve been skeptical as to the utility of the project, which was billed as a &#34;Stern Report for Biodiversity&#34; when it was begun three years ago. &amp;nbsp;Nicholas Stern&#39;s report on the economic impact of climate change could be reduced to a few numbers - the cost of mitigation, and the cost of action, tons of carbon released and its concentration in the atmosphere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New approaches to looking at water-related financial risks</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-21-new-approaches-to-looking-at-water-related-financial-risks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-21-new-approaches-to-looking-at-water-related-financial-risks/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s an article in the Times today about risks that utilities face due to water shortages.&amp;nbsp; The story is based on a new report from Ceres and PricewaterhouseCoopers which claims that bond ratings agencies haven&#39;t adequately incorporated these risks into their ratings, causing an over-valuation of bonds issued by cities and public utilities. &amp;nbsp; Ceres and PwC base their analyses on future projections of water supply and demand, which in turn are predicted from demographic and climate predictions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading philosophy can get you down</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-18-reading-philosophy-can-get-you-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-18-reading-philosophy-can-get-you-down/</guid>
      <description>Reading Lawrence Hinman&#39;s &#34;Ethics, a Pluralistic Approach to Moral Theory,&#34; I came across this quote in a discussion of valuing utility to future generations:
 ...they do not yet exist - and, depending on our actions, they may never exist.
 I stared at this for a long time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saving more than species at Nagoya</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-16-saving-more-than-species-at-nagoya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-16-saving-more-than-species-at-nagoya/</guid>
      <description>There&#39;s been a whole lot of interesting stuff coming out this week related the Conference of the Parties (COP 10) for the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) going on in Nagoya, Japan right now. &amp;nbsp; CBD&#39;s goal was to slow the loss of biodiversity loss by 2010, but that goal was not achieved, and nations are hammering out how to revive the CBD with new goals for 2020.
At a prepatory meeting in May, governments agreed on 20 more specific draft targets, which aim to be &amp;ldquo;SMART&amp;rdquo; - specific, measurable, ambitious, realistic, and time-bound.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the carbon market needs ecologists</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-16-why-the-carbon-market-needs-ecologists/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-16-why-the-carbon-market-needs-ecologists/</guid>
      <description>&amp;nbsp;
Last week the Journal of Applied Ecology had an article titled, &#34;How can ecologists help realize the potential of payments for carbon in tropical forest countries?&#34; It outlined ways that ecologists could make themselves useful in Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and Degradation (REDD).&amp;nbsp; The article was aimed at ecologists, but I&#39;m going to give the authors&#39; insights a different twist.&amp;nbsp; In the interest of the welfare of my colleagues, I&#39;d like to point out to the carbon community that ecological expertise is worth some money.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does ecology tell us that some species are worth more than others?</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-11-does-ecology-tell-us-that-some-species-are-worth-more-than-o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-11-does-ecology-tell-us-that-some-species-are-worth-more-than-o/</guid>
      <description>I just read a great paper by Michael Soul&amp;eacute; et. al. discussing the management implications some ideas in ecology that have outpaced environmental policy.
The authors, a mix of ecologists and conservationists,&amp;nbsp; argue that some species, which they call &#34;strongly interacting species,&#34; deserve higher priority in conservation because of their unique roles in ecosystems.&amp;nbsp; These species have gone by many names in the ecological literature, including &#34;keystone species,&#34; and &#34;ecosystem engineers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liability for stolen ecosystem services</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-11-liability-for-stolen-ecosystem-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-11-liability-for-stolen-ecosystem-services/</guid>
      <description>In Wasior, Papua New Guinea, flash floods have killed well over 100 people.&amp;nbsp; Conservation groups blame illegal logging activities in the Wasior area for exacerbating the flooding, and the Indonesian government is investigating this possibility.
While this case is still uncertain, it is clear that deforestation leads to increased flood risk.&amp;nbsp; CJA Bradshaw and colleagues published an article in Global Change Biology showing that at 10% increase in deforestation leads to a 4%-28% increase in flood frequencies in developing countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring resilience to climate-change driven crop failure</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-08-measuring-resilience-to-climate-change-driven-crop-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-08-measuring-resilience-to-climate-change-driven-crop-failure/</guid>
      <description>A number of news outlets have picked up on a new article in Environmental Research Letters by Andy Challinor and a team at the University at Leeds.&amp;nbsp; The standard headline is &#34;Crop Failures to Increase With Climate Change,&#34; but I think the much more interesting part of the research is the author&#39;s creation of a vulnerability index based on the historical crop data in China.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, they looked at periods of drought in the past, and examined how well farmers were able to mitigate the drought&#39;s effects through additional labor or technology:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In honeybee collapse, cure the patient, not just the disease.</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-07-in-honeybee-collapse-cure-the-patient-not-just-the-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-07-in-honeybee-collapse-cure-the-patient-not-just-the-disease/</guid>
      <description>My first published article examined implications of the massive collapse of honeybee populations on business, so I feel compelled to comment on the latest development in the hunt for the cause of colony collapse disorder (CCD).
There is a new article out on the subject by a team led by University of Montana researchers and the US Army Chemical Biological center.&amp;nbsp; Using proteomic sequencing, they found two culprits in the bodies of dead bees: invertebrate iridescent virus (IIV), a long-stranded DNA virus, and Nosema, a fungal spore.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid evolution as a warning sign</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-02-rapid-evolution-as-a-warning-sign/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-02-rapid-evolution-as-a-warning-sign/</guid>
      <description>One of the emerging themes of my course in rapid environmental change is how humans have accelerated natural processes to a pace never seen before in earth&#39;s history.&amp;nbsp; For instance, climate change has in the past occurred at scales of tens of thousands of years or longer, but man-made climate change in happening at the pace of decades or centuries.
Less well-known is the effect we can have on the speed of evolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harmful algal blooms highlight risks from cascading ecological collapse</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-10-01-harmful-algal-blooms-highlight-risks-from-cascading-ecologic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-10-01-harmful-algal-blooms-highlight-risks-from-cascading-ecologic/</guid>
      <description>Harmful algal blooms (HABs) are scary things.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The occur when populations of algae explode in coastal environments.&amp;nbsp; The algae suck up the oxygen and release neurotoxins into the water, and even the local air.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Fisheries and beaches have to be shut down.&amp;nbsp; People have been killed.&amp;nbsp; HABs aren&#39;t predictable, but its clear that they more damaging and more common than they were in the past due to nutrient pollution in coastal areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Payments for ecosystem services are great, unless we do them enough to make a difference</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-09-30-payments-for-ecosystem-services-are-great-unless-we-do-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-09-30-payments-for-ecosystem-services-are-great-unless-we-do-them/</guid>
      <description>The usually excellent Mongabay ran the scare headline, &#34;Could industrial interests ruin payments for environmental services?&#34; on a piece in Tropical Conservation Science.&amp;nbsp; Thankfully the authors of the paper being reported on, &#34;Upscaling Payments for Environmental Services (PES): Critical issues&#34; are a little less alarmist.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, I think that that their concern about large companies getting involved in ecosystem service markets is overwrought.
 PES have traditionally been conceived and applied in contexts where the providers of the service are populations (as opposed to industrial companies) &amp;ndash; fishermen, farmers, forest dwellers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A species is priceless - does that mean that it is worth nothing or everything?</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-09-27-a-species-is-priceless-does-that-mean-that-it-is-worth-nothi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-09-27-a-species-is-priceless-does-that-mean-that-it-is-worth-nothi/</guid>
      <description>Richard Conniff﻿ has an eloquent piece up at Yale Environment 360 discussing how we place economic value on species and biodiversity in general.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; He tells the story of how farmers in India inadverdantly killed 99% of the country&#39;s vultures by feeding their cattle anti-inflamatory drugs.&amp;nbsp; The drugs caused renal failure in vultures feeding on the carcasses.&amp;nbsp; With the vultures gone, India&#39;s feral dog population skyrocketed, and the feral dogs gave many people rabies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk, Insurance, LUST, and Fish</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-09-24-risk-insurance-lust-and-fish/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-09-24-risk-insurance-lust-and-fish/</guid>
      <description>Two papers crossed my desk yesterday highlighting the role insurance can play in mitigating environmental risk.&amp;nbsp; The first, by Yin et. al. in Risk Analysis, discusses three appoaches to mitigating the risk of leaking underground storage tanks (a problem with the fantastic acronym LUST).&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Large fines for spills, as it turns out, are not a particularly efficient enforcement tool, as most LUSTs are owned by small businesses like gas stations that would likely go bankrupt before paying all the fines and cleanup costs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Money Quote</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-09-23-money-quote/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-09-23-money-quote/</guid>
      <description>Pavan Sukhdev, Head of the UNEP Green Economy Initiative,﻿ and previously Managing Director in the Global Markets Division at Deutsche Bank, has some remarkably lucid things to say about fisheries in this month&#39;s Frontiers in Ecology and Environment:
 &#34;Economics is the science of scarce resources. What is scarce here as a resource is not fishing capacity &amp;ndash; in which every year we invest more, as a result of the subsidies that are targeted largely at the bigger fleets and the trawler fleets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In the News:  Hysteresis in Coral Reefs</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-09-21-in-the-news-hysteresis-in-coral-reefs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-09-21-in-the-news-hysteresis-in-coral-reefs/</guid>
      <description>As this is my first crack at an explanatory post, I&#39;d appreciate feedback on both the level and quality of the writing.&amp;nbsp; Thanks!

One of the things I plan to do on this blog is delve a little deeper into ecological stories that arise in the news.&amp;nbsp; A great opportunity popped up today in a front-page story in the New York Times about coral reef bleaching.&amp;nbsp; It seems that record temperatures this year are causing one of the largest coral die-offs in history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Species in a Bucket</title>
      <link>/archives/2010-09-17-species-in-a-bucket/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>grixor@gmail.com (Trang Le)</author>
      <guid>/archives/2010-09-17-species-in-a-bucket/</guid>
      <description>I am not really a wildlife person. My own work and perspective is systemic; I study global biogeochemical cycles, mathematical systems theory, and other large, shapeless, abstract ideas. I am terrible at recognizing and remembering the names of plants and animals in the field. Also, while I enjoy an aesthetic and spiritual connection to nature, my own brand of environmentalism leans towards saving ourselves - nature for nature&#39;s sake has usually taken second place in my mind.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>